Guide to the James Martin Bell Papers, 1768-1870 and undated RL.00100
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Martin Bell papers
1768-1870 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bell, James Martin
RL.00100
15 Linear Feet 40 boxes
Lawyer, political leader, ironmaster, railroad promoter, and banker, of Hollidaysburg, Pennsylvania. Correspondence and business papers reflecting the major part played by Bell and his family in the economic development of central Pennsylvania and other areas. Among the subjects dealt with are the building of internal improvements, the charcoal iron industry in the Juniata Valley, land titles and speculation, and early growth of the Pennsylvania Railroad under J. Edgar Thomson and others, tariff bills, the economic cycle of booms and depressions, the evolution of the monetary and banking system, telegraph companies, coal mining, Lake Superior copper mining, and Bell's active interest in Whig and Republican Party politics. Papers of the Civil War period illustrate the impact of the conflict on the business community in the North, and on the people of Pennsylvania during Confederate raids and invasions. Some papers relate to tests of Pennsylvania iron made at the Washington Navy Yard by Captain Dahlgren, to Bell's service as agent of Jay Cooke in floating Federal loans in Pennsylvania, and to the effect of the war on the banking system. Included are two early railroad broadsides from Bellefontaine and Indiana Railroad and Union Pacific Railroad (1856 and 1867).
13,604 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The James Martin Bell Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1956.
Collection Overview
Correspondence and business papers reflecting the major part played by Bell and his family in the economic development of central Pennsylvania and other areas. Among the subjects dealt with are the building of internal improvements, the charcoal iron industry in the Juniata Valley, land titles and speculation, and early growth of the Pennsylvania Railroad under J. Edgar Thomson and others, tariff bills, the economic cycle of booms and depressions, the evolution of the monetary and banking system, telegraph companies, coal mining, Lake Superior copper mining, and Bell's active interest in Whig and Republican Party politics. Papers of the Civil War period illustrate the impact of the conflict on the business community in the North, and on the people of Pennsylvania during Confederate raids and invasions. Some papers relate to tests of Pennsylvania iron made at the Washington Navy Yard by Captain Dahlgren, to Bell's service as agent of Jay Cooke in floating Federal loans in Pennsylvania, and to the effect of the war on the banking system. Included are two early railroad broadsides from Bellefontaine and Indiana Railroad and Union Pacific Railroad (1856 and 1867).
Pennsylvania -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Pennsylvania -- Economic conditions; Telegraph -- Pennsylvania -- History; Public works -- Pennsylvania; Iron industry and trade -- Pennsylvania; Railroads -- Pennsylvania; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Economic aspects; Copper industry and trade -- Superior, Lake; Coal mines and mining -- Pennsylvania; Banks and banking -- United States; Whig Party (Pa.); Republican Party (Pa.); Thomson, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1808-1874
- Correspondence, 1768-1870, 18 boxes
  - Letters, 1768-1834 July (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1834 Aug.-1837 May (Box 2)
  - Letters, 1837 June-1839 Feb. (Box 3)
  - Letters, 1839 Mar.-1840 Apr. 13 (Box 4)
  - Letters, 1840 Apr. 14-1842 Aug. (Box 5)
  - Letters, 1842 Sept.-1843 July (Box 6)
  - Letters, 1843 Aug.-1844 July (Box 7)
  - Letters, 1844 Aug.-1854 Aug. (Box 8)
  - Letters, 1845 Sept.-1846 May (Box 9)
  - Letters, 1846 June-1848 July (Box 10)
  - Letters, 1848 Aug.-1852 (Box 11)
  - Letters, 1853-1855 Nov. (Box 12)
  - Letters, 1855 Dec.-1857 (Box 13)
  - Letters, 1858-1859 (Box 14)
  - Letters, 1860-1862 (Box 15)
  - Letters, 1863-1865 (Box 16)
  - Letters, 1866-1868 (Box 17)
  - Letters, 1869-1870 and undated (Box 18)
- Legal Papers, 1755-1896 and undated, 10 boxes
  - Legal Papers (cases), 1755-1844 (Box 19)
  - Legal Papers (cases), 1766-1848 (Box 20)
  - Legal Papers (cases), 1771-1852 (Box 21)
  - Legal Papers (cases), 1794-1847 (Box 22)
  - Legal Papers (cases), 1811-1858 (Box 23)
  - Legal Papers (cases), 1832-1859 (Box 24)
  - Legal Papers (cases), 1842-1869 (Box 25)
  - Legal Papers (personal), 1823-1869 (Box 26)
  - Legal Papers (misc.), 1779-1843 (Box 27)
  - Legal Papers (misc.), 1844-1896 and undated (Box 28)
- Printed Material, 3 boxes
  - Printed materials (Box 29-31)
- Bills and Receipts, 1765-1870s, 6 boxes
  - Bills, Receipts, etc., 1765-1830s (Box 32)
  - Bills, Receipts, etc., 1830s (Box 33)
  - Bills, Receipts, etc., 1840s (Box 34)
  - Bills, Receipts, etc., 1840s-1850s (Box 35)
  - Bills, Receipts, etc., 1850s (Box 36)
  - Bills, Receipts, etc., 1860s-1870s and undated (Box 37)
- Volumes Series, 3 boxes
  - Volumes (Box 38-40)
- Oversize Materials, 1 folder
  Scope and Contents note
  Two railroad broadsides: opening of Union Pacific westward line to San Francisco, prob. 1867 (large); announcement for Bellefontaine and Indiana Railroad/Penssylvania Railroad, 1856 (small). Both are in black, white, and red print.
  - Oversized materials (Oversize-folder 1)